Pola Nirenska Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Subject Files, 1933-1982 (Box 23)
  The Subject Files series consists of Nirenska's dance school, dance company, and related files containing publicity, programs, clippings, and writings; also a file of gardening materials ("New plants").
  Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Dance recital publicity, 1958-82 (Box-folder 23/1)
  - Dance school, 1960-68 (Box-folder 23/2-4)
  - An evening of choreography by Pola Nirenska, 1990 July 28-29 (Box-folder 23/5)
  - Für Pola, 1933-58 [writings, programs, and publicity from outside U.S.] (Box-folder 28/24-27)
  - Loose single reprints [clippings and programs], 1964-81 (Box-folder 23/6)
  - New plants (Box-folder 23/7)
  - Pola Nirenska Dance Company -- programs, leaflets, etc., 1958-66 (Box-folder 23/8)
  - Reviews [and programs/publicity], 1948-63 (Box-folder 23/9)
  - Washington Dance Company, 1958-66 (Box-folder 23/10)
- Personal Papers (Box 24, Box 25)
  The Personal Papers series consists of three categories arranged alphabetically and sorted chronologically at the folder level as applicable: addresses and cards, bibliographic cards, business, medical, and miscellaneous.
  Arranged alphabetically and sorted chronologically
  - Addresses and cards (Box-folder 24/1)
  - Bibliographic cards [Note: Topics are as follows: Art, cookery, dance, dictionaries and encyclopedias, fairy tales and legends, gymnastics and health, literature, love and marriage, music, philosophy and psychology, poetry, politics and history, religion and religion-philosophy, theater and costumes, etc., miscellaneous] (Box 25)
  - Business (Box-folder 24/2)
  - Medical (Box-folder 24/3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 24/4)
- Awards, 1934, 1980, 1987, 1991 (Box 24, Box 29, Box 30)
  The Awards series consists of a certificate of appreciation, and a diploma.
  - Diploma, Internationaler Tanz = Wettbewerb und Volkstanztreffen Wien, 1934 June 16 (Box-folder 30/18)
  - Award, Metropolitan Dance Association, 1980 (Box-folder 24/5)
  - Award, St. Patrick's Senior Center, for the intergenerational contribution of Pola Nirenska to the cultural life of the greater Washington area, 1987 (Box-folder 29/18)
  - Certificate of appreciation, National Law Enforcement Officers Memorial Fund, 1991 Aug. 16 (Box-folder 24/6)
- Realia, 1985, undated (Box 26, Box 27)
  The Realia series consists of a medal from the 200th anniversary of the Polish Ballet and other items.
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Medal, 200th anniversary of Polish Ballet, 1985 (Box 26)
  - Sea shell (Box 27)
- Books and Articles (Box [shelf])
  The Books and Articles series is represented by two subseries: Books; Articles & Clippings. The Books subseries consists of monographs related to dance, religion, and history. The Articles & Clippings subseries consists of magazines, articles and clippings (not about Nirenska), mostly dance-related.
  Arranged alphabetically by author and title
  - Books (Box [shelf])
    - Aubel, Hermann and Marianne, Der Künstlerische Tanz unserer Zeit
    - Bainton, Roland H., The horizon history of Christianity
    - Behr, Walter, Das hatte ich zu sagen...
    - Bénard, Th., L'Année préparatoire d'histoire sainte
    - Bie, Oskar, Der Tanz
    - Boehn, Max von, Der Tanz
    - Cartier-Bresson, Henri, Les danses à Bali
    - Cato (Owen Frank), Guilty men
    - Chesterton, G. K., St. Thomas Aquinas
    - Clarke, C. P. S., Short history of the Christian church
    - Dahlke, Paul, Buddhismus als Weltanschauung
    - Daniel-Rops, Henri, This is the mass
    - Daudet, Alphonse, Die Abenteuer des Herrn Tartarin aus Tarascon
    - Delius, Rudolf von, Tanz und Erotica
    - Diebold, Bernhard, Habima
    - Duncan, Isadora, Der Tanz der Zukunft
    - Dzikowski, Stanislaw, O tancu
    - Elleniko chorodrama, 1950-1960
    - Freund, Liesel, Monographien der Ausbildungsschulen für Tanz und tänzrische Öperbildung, Band 1: Berlin
    - Gert, Valeska, Mein Weg
    - Gibbon, Edward, Christianity and the decline of Rome
    - Gobineau, Graf, Asiatische Novellen
    - Graham, Dom Aelred, Catholicism and the world today
    - Gray, Rev. Ronald, This is your mass
    - Green, Lili, Einführung in das Wesen unserer Gesten und Bewegungen
    - Gregor, Joseph, Kulturgeschichte des Balletts. Autographed with note, Wien, 1947 Nov.
    - Gunther, John, and Bernard Quint, Days to remember: America 1945-1955
    - Hersey, John, The wall
    - Hildenbrandt, Fred, Die Tänzerin Valeska Gert. 1930 Dresden
    - The holy bible, light of the world edition
    - Höver, Otto, Javanische Schattenspiele
    - Hughes, Philip, A popular history of the Reformation
    - Kellermann, Bernhard, Japanische Tänze. 1930 Dresden
    - Khayyám, Omar, Trans. by Edward Fitzgerald, Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám
    - Killgallon, James, and Gerard Weber, Life in Christ
    - Klingenbeck, Fritz, Die Tänzerin Rosalia Chladek
    - Knox, Ronald, The belief of Catholics
    - Kochanowicz, Jan, Wstep do nauki o teatrze
    - Kolb, Dr. Med. Rudolf, Magen und Darm
    - Kubin, Alfred, Dämonen und Nachtgesichte. Autographed by Nirenska
    - Laban, Rudolf von, Des Kindes Gymnastik und Tanz
    - Laban, Rudolf von, Die Welt des Tänzers
    - Levinson, André, La Argentina: A study in Spanish dancing
    - Levinson, André, La danse d'aujourd'hui
    - Liguori, St. Alphonsus, The way of the cross
    - Linder, Kurt, Die Verwandlungen der Mary Wigman
    - Lloyd, Roger, The mastery of evil
    - Mackiewicz, Stanislaw, Historja Polski
    - Mamontowicz-Lojek, Bozena, Terpsychora i lekkie muzy
    - May, Joseph, Stehen Sie fest auf Ihren Füssen?
    - Medau, Hinrich, Deutsche Gymnastik
    - Muther, Richard, Die Kunst, Band 43: Der Tanz als Kunstwerk von Oscar Bie
    - Nerman, Einar, Darlings of the gods: in music hall, revue, and musical comedy
    - Netzer, Dr. Shlomo, A thousand years of history of the Jews of Poland
    - Newman, Dora, Elfenblüten
    - Oberdörffer, Med. H. J., Rhythmische Atem-Gymnastik-Schule
    - Pawlowa, Anna, Anna Pawlowa
    - Pirchan, Emil, Harald Kreutzberg
    - Prucha, F. P., and Gerald Ellard, ed., The sacred ceremonies of holy week
    - Remarque, Erich Maria, Droga powrotna
    - Rheinhardt, E. A., Eleonora Duse
    - Sachar, Abram Leon, A history of the Jews, fifth edition
    - Storck, Karl, Der Tanz
    - Strauss, Richard, Die Musik, Band 47/48: Der Künstlerische Tanz von Werner Suhr
    - Swieto tanca artystycznego
    - Tairoff, Alexander, Das entfesselte Theater 1937 Dresden
    - The Talmud of Jerusalem
    - Die Tänzerin Mary Wigman
    - Terpis, Max, Tanz und Tänzer. "In appreciation of your art of dancing" Katia Michalovsky; 1947 Mar. 27
    - Toller, Ernst, Joseph Roth, and Alfons Goldschmidt, Das Moskauer Jüdische Akademische. Theater, 1931
    - Walsh, John, This is Catholicism
    - Way of the cross: meditations of Pope John Paul II
    - Wiesenthal, Grete, Die ersten Schritte, 1947
    - Wigman, Mary, Deutsche Tanzkunst. Autographed by Wigman; 1935 Dresden
    - Wigman, Mary, Komposition
    - Wigman, Mary, Die sieben Tänze des Lebens
    - Williams, Charles, The forgiveness of sins
    - Winther, Fritz, Körperbildung als Kunft und Pflicht
    - Wolkonski, Ks. Sergjusz, Czlowiek wyrazisty
    - Zundel, Maurice, The splendour of the liturgy
  - Articles and Clippings (Box-folder 24/7-9, Box-folder 28/28)
    - Dance magazine, 62, no. 6 (1988 June) (Box-folder 24/7)
    - Tanzdrama Magazin, no. 1 (1987 4. Quartal) (Box-folder 24/8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 24/9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 28/28)
Appendix A: Works by Nirenska
American folk suite (music: accompanied by Elizabeth Wilson Hughes, voice and dulcimer)
"The three sisters" (music: folk song adapted from "The old lord of the Northern Sea," from the John Jacob Niles Collection)
"Complaining old woman" (music: Elizabeth Wilson Hughes; text: incomplete folk poem, from the Vance Randolph collection)
"Yankee girl"
"If I had a ribbon bow"
"Maid freed from the gallows"
"Old woman, old man"
"Pigeons and pain"
Avenue of escape
"Brandy" (music: Béla Bartók)
"Champagne" (music: Claude Debussy)
"Absinth" (music: Aaron Copland)
Bag lady (music: Claude Bolling, Jean-Pierre Rampal)
Barbaric suite (music: Priaulx Rainier)
"The dance of fear"
"The dance of longing"
"The dance of joy"
Dancer's dilemma (music: arranged by Kotowska)
Departures (music: Heitor Villa-Lobos)
Dirge ("In memory of those I loved who are no more") (music: Concerto grosso no. 1, by Ernest Bloch; costume designer: Terri Prell); second section of Holocaust tetralogy
The divided self (music: Symphony no. 4, by Roger Goeb; performed by Japan Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra)
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey; music: J. S. Bach; costume designers: Cheryl Koehler, Ellen Gray Denker), 1968
"Allegro"
"Adagio"
"Allegro"
Encircled (music: Heitor Villa-Lobos)
Encounters and goodbyes (music: Sonata no. 3 [?], by Norman Dello Joio)
The eternal fool ("We speak of a young girl, Pierrot and the moon") (music: Abba Nieman)
Exits (music: Evelyn Lohoefer; quotations: Dylan Thomas; costume designer: Terri Prell)
"Rage, rage against dying of the light"
"Bless me now with your fierce tears, I pray... "
"Do not go gently into that good night"
Faith (music: Clague)
Felina -- catty woman (music: Da Costa)
The four horsemen of the apocalypse (music: Anton Webern)
"Humanity"
"Power"
"Plague"
"War"
"Death"
Greek washer-girl (music: old Greek round, arranged by R. Cavalho)
Homeless child (Unwanted child) (music: Adda Heynessen)
I found my grandmother dead (music: Arnold Schoenberg)
In the sun (music: Béla Bartók)
Italian concerto (music: J. S. Bach)
Jubilee (musical revue; music: arranged by John Toohill)
The lament (music: lullaby, early 17th century around the time of the Great Plague; vocals: Julia Humphries)
Laughter (music: Eugène Bozza)
Life (sometimes referred to as Whatever begins also ends) (music: Concerto grosso no. 1, by Ernest Bloch; costume designer: Terri Prell; quote: Seneca), first section of Holocaust tetralogy
Life is so daily (music: Lukas Foss)
Longing (music: "La plus que lente," by Claude Debussy; piano: Peter Frankel; costume designer: Terri Prell)
Lullaby (music: Ignacy Jan Paderewski)
Mad girl (music: Frederico Mompou)
Mazur (national Polish dance)
Menuet (music: Frédéric Chopin)
The old and the new (music: traditional, vocals by Richard Tucker)
Once over lightly (musical revue; music: arranged by Edward Cashman and Edward Shamaphy)
Out of sorts (music: Claude Bolling)
Peasant Lullaby (music: Polish folk tunes, arranged by R. Cavalho)
Picnic (music: Virgil Thomson)
La puerta del vino (The gate of wine) (music: Claude Debussy)
"Rhythm in 3/4"
"Rhythm in 4/4"
Russia: the transparent apple and the silver saucer, "Snow in Siberia" (solo choreographed by Nirenska for Liz Lerman; all other choreography by Lerman)
St. Bridget: stained-glass window (The patron of weavers and spinners) (music: French folk songs, arranged by Benjamin Britten)
Sarabande for the dead queen (music: Claude Debussy)
A scarecrow remembers (music: Adda Heynessen, Gorney)
Shakespearean suite (music: Sergei Prokofiev)
Shepherd boy (music: Greek folk song)
Shout (music: "Hatred of the filthy bomb," by Lou Harrison); third section of Holocaust tetralogy
Stars & planets (music: George Crumb)
Stillpoint (music: "The unanswered question," by Charles Ives), 1990
Strange visit (music: Béla Bartók)
Studies in modern dance
"Floor swings"
"Primitive player"
"Birds"
"Isolation"
Sweet william (musical; music: by Edward Cashman)
They never came back (music: G. Orville Trondson)
Three sculptures (music: Evelyn Lohoefer; costume designers: Stan Fowler, Sandy Asay, Pola Nirenska; set designers: Stan Fowler, Alex Rounds), commissioned by Washington Dance Repertory
"The eternal insomnia of the earth"
"Amity"
"The knot"
Three women (costume designer: Gayle Behrman Jaster), 1987
I. (music: Anthony Davis)
II. (music: Miles Davis)
III. (music: Ella Fitzgerald with Duke Ellington)
Tired magician (music: William Russel, Henry Dixon Cowell)
The train (music: "Suntreader," by Carl Ruggles); last section of Holocaust tetralogy
Trapped (music: "Satyagraha," by Philip Glass)
Trip (music: Modern Jazz Quartet)
Two queens (The queen) (music: G. Orville Trondson)
Vigil by the sea (Fated vigil)
"Waiting" (music: G. Orville Trondson)
"Lament" (music: song attributed to William Byrd)
Village beauty (music: Polish folk tunes, arranged by R. Cavalho)
Web (music: Jon Hassell)
Woman #1 (music: Anthony Davis) see also Three women
Wounded (music: Concerto for piano and orchestra, "Allucinante," by Alberto Ginastera; costume designer: Terri Prell)
Appendix B: Audiovisual Materials
Audiovisual materials are located in the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division (M/B/RS) of the Library of Congress
Videotapes
1 Exuberance
dancer: Laura Schandelmeier
music: "Little fugue in g minor," J. S. Bach
videographer: Laziza
Nirenska choreographed Exuberance for Laura Schandelmeier, her next door neighbor. The work is a music visualization in the style of Doris Humphrey. The performance was recorded in Nirenska's basement studio.
2 Last concert 1984: Stars & planet and other dances, choreography by Pola Nirenska, Marvin Theater, George Washington University, March 10, 1984
Tired magician (premiere)
music: William Russel, Henry Dixon Cowell
dancers: Nirenska, Diane Floyd, Susan Hannen, Meryl W. Shapiro, Jan Tievsky
Encounters and goodbyes (premiere, original concept 1965)
music: Sonata no. 3 [?], Norman Dello Joio
dancers: Rima Faber, mother; Susan Hannen, child; Jan Tievsky, bad influence; Diane Floyd, good influence; Greg Reynolds, young man
Jewish song (The old and the new) (premiere)
music: traditional, performed by Richard Tucker
dancer: Liz Lerman
Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Jeanne Feeney, Diane Floyd, Susan Hannen, Meryl W. Shapiro, Stephanie Simmons, Jan Tievsky, Rima Faber
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Jeanne Feeney, Diane Floyd, Susan Hannen, Meryl W. Shapiro, Stephanie Simmons, Jan Tievsky, Rima Faber
Weed (Trip) (1983)
music: The Modern Jazz Quartet
dancer: Susan Hannen
Stars & planet (premiere, dedicated to Louis Horst)
music: George Crumb
dancers: Liz Lerman, Earth; Greg Reynolds, Moon; Patrick Scully, Sun; Diane Floyd, Bollux; Susan Hannen, Castor; Jan Tievsky, Taurus Hyader; Northern Star Polaris, Stephanie Simmons; Tobie Hoffman, Comet
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
lighting and stage manager, lighting designer: David Madden
sound technician: Judy Tyson
production manager: Martin Petersilia
The concert was partially funded by a grant from the National Endowment for the Arts.
3 Web, TV version
music: Jon Hassell
dancer: Shawn Womack
The performance was videotaped for television. There are special effects such as double images and freeze frames.
4 Everything ["Kennedy Center 1988" on box]
Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Weed (Trip) (1983)
music: The Modern Jazz Quartet
dancer: Susan Hannen
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Stars & planet (1984, dedicated to Louis Horst)
music: George Crumb
dancers: Liz Lerman, Earth; Greg Reynolds, Moon; Patrick Scully, Sun; Diane Floyd, Bollux; Susan Hannen, Castor; Jan Tievsky, Taurus Hyader; Northern Star Polaris, Stephanie Simmons; Tobie Hoffman, Comet
The videotape is mislabeled. The recordings are most likely of rehearsals. During Life, Nirenska can be heard instructing the lighting designer. Only a few seconds of Stars & planet are recorded. Attached to the box is a note: "Love, Ron."
5 Trapped, "Snow in Siberia" (EP)
Trapped
music: Satyagraha, Philip Glass
dancer: Jan Tievsky
Russia: the transparent apple and the silver saucer, "Snow in Siberia"
music: "Groundswell," Vladimir Cosma
dancer: Liz Lerman
The quality of the recording is poor. "Snow in Siberia" is the second movement of the second act from Russia. The solo is the fifth dance Nirenska choreographed for Lerman.
6 5/3/96 Dancefest '86 Glen Echo, Shout, panel discussion with Hanya Holm
Shout (1986)
music: Hatred of the filthy bomb, Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
videographer: Harmony Vanover
Panel discussion with Hanya Holm, Erika Thimey, Sali Ann Kriegsman, and Nirenska
The recording is from Dancefest 1986, in celebration of National Dance Week, held in Glen Echo Park, Maryland, May 3-5. During the panel discussion, Nirenska read a tribute to Holm discussing her relationship with Holm and the Wigman Schule. A copy of the script is in Scrapbook no. 12.
7 Choreography by Pola Nirenska, Woman, Shout, Sun. June 14, Dance Place
Three women (1987)
I. music: Anthony Davis
II. music: Miles Davis
III. music: Ella Fitzgerald with Duke Ellington
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Gayle Behrman Jaster
Shout (1986)
music: Hatred of the filthy bomb, Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Beth Burkhardt
8 Concert, 1982: solo, Dirge, Bach (LP)
"An evening of choreography" by Pola Nirenska, March 9, 1982, 8:00 p.m., Marvin Theater
Wounded (premiere)
music: Concerto for piano and orchestra, "Allucinante," Alberto Ginastera
dancer: Betsy Eagan
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Whatever begins also ends (premiere)
Life (1982)
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
Life dancers: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
Dirge dancers: Rima Faber, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Three sculptures (1965)
"The eternal insomnia of earth"
"Amity"
"The knot"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
"The eternal insomnia of earth"
dancer: Colette Yglesias
"Amity"
dancers: Betsy Eagan, Stephanie Simmons, Carrie Wilcox
"The knot"
dancers: Letitia Carter, Susan Hannen, Jenifer Litwin
costume designers: Stan Fowler, Sandy Asay, Nirenska
set designers: Stan Fowler, Alex Rounds
Commissioned by Washington Dance Repertory
Exits
"Rage, rage against dying of the light" (1968)
"Bless me now with your fierce tears, I pray..."
"Do not go gently into that good night"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Liz Lerman
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
quotations: Dylan Thomas
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey, 1968)
music: J. S. Bach
dancers: Susan Hannen, Ellen Gray Denker, Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Jenifer Litwin, Stephanie Simmons, Carrie Wilcox
The quality of the recording is poor. Much of the performance is not visible because of darkness. Longing was the first work performed at the concert, but it is not on the recording. Nirenska can be heard commenting on lighting and various other aspects of the performance.
9 Liz (SP)
The Dance Exchange and Performance Company and The Dancers of the Third Age, June 13-14, 1985, Caplin Theatre, Sidwell Friends School
Russia: the transparent apple and the silver saucer
choreography: Liz Lerman, solo by Nirenska
original music: David Bishop
dancers: Susan Barnett, Jeff Bliss, Eric Bobrow, Mary Buckley, Debra Caplowe, Bob Fogelgren, Velerie Hallenbeck, Louise Haskin, Judith Jourdin, Liz Lerman, Lory Leshin, Monica Lewis, Anne McDonald, Jessica Rea, Hannah Rosenthal, Charlie Rother, Kathy Robens Siegel, Louisa Winer, Don Zuckerman
lighting designer: Susan E. Landess
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
art direction: Kathy Suter
projection programming: Steve Spector
sound: Josh Schneider, Monica Peterschmidt
stage manager: Joan L. Hampton
administrative director: Craig Impink
Russia includes "Snow in Siberia," a solo choreographed by Nirenska for Lerman. A few parts are cut momentarily.
10 Dance master copy [copy of #8] (LP)
Dress rehearsal, "An evening of choreography" by Pola Nirenska, March 9, 1982, 8:00 p.m., Marvin Theater
Wounded (1982)
music: Concerto for piano and orchestra, "Allucinante," Alberto Ginastera
dancer: Betsy Eagan
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Whatever begins also ends
Life (1982)
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
Life dancers: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
Dirge dancers: Rima Faber, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Three sculptures
"The eternal insomnia of the earth"
"Amity"
"The knot"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
costume designers: Stan Fowler, Sandy Asay, Nirenska
set designers: Stan Fowler, Alex Rounds
"The eternal insomnia of the earth"
dancer: Colette Yglesias
"Amity"
dancers: Betsy Eagan, Stephanie Simmons, Carrie Wilcox
"The knot"
dancers: Letitia Carter, Susan Hannen, Jenifer Litwin
Commissioned by Washington Dance Repertory
Exits
"Rage, rage against dying of the light" (1968)
"Bless me now with your fierce tears, I pray..."
"Do not go gently into that good night"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Liz Lerman
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
quotations: Dylan Thomas
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey, 1968)
music: J. S. Bach
dancers: Susan Hannen, Ellen Gray Denker, Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Jenifer Litwin, Stephanie Simmons, Carrie Wilcox
The quality of the recording is poor. Much of the performance is not visible because of darkness. Longing was the first work performed at the concert, but it is not on the recording. Nirenska can be heard commenting in the background on lighting and various other aspects of the performance.
11 Pola Nirenska concert at Dance Place
The divided self
music: Symphony no. 4, Roger Goeb; performed by the Japan Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra
dancers: Jan Tievsky, Cheryl Koehler
Longing
music: La plus que lente, Claude Debussy; performed by Peter Frankel
dancer: Susan Hannen
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Three sculptures, "The eternal insomnia of the earth"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Colette Yglesias
costume designers: Stan Fowler, Sandy Asay, Nirenska
set designers: Stan Fowler, Alex Rounds
Commissioned by Washington Dance Repertory
Exits
"Rage, rage against dying of the light" (1968)
"Bless me now with your fierce tears, I pray..."
"Do not go gently into that good night"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Liz Lerman
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
quotations: Dylan Thomas
Weed (Trip) (1983)
music: Modern Jazz Quartet
dancer: Cathy Payne
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Jewish song (The old and the new) (1984)
music: traditional, performed by Richard Tucker
dancer: Liz Lerman
Three women (1987)
I. music: Anthony Davis
II. music: Miles Davis
III. music: Ella Fitzgerald with Duke Ellington
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Gayle Behrman Jaster
Shout (1986)
music: Hatred of the filthy bomb, Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Beth Burkhardt
Whatever begins also ends
Life (1982)
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
Life dancers: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie
Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
Dirge dancers: Rima Faber, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey, 1968)
music: J. S. Bach
The videotape is fragile due to a repaired splice.
12 Jackson (EP)
Television documentary on Michael Jackson
BAD, recorded from WETA 26, Washington, DC
executive producers: Michael Jackson, Harry Ufland, Frank Dileo
producer: Quincy Jones, Barbara De Fina
writer: Richard Price
director: Martin Scorsese
Clip of The teahouse of the August moon
Commercials
"Alive from off center"
Air dance landings, Michael Schwartz and Elizabeth Streb
New puritan dances, Michael Clark
The daytime moon, Min Tanaka
Documentary on Pepsico Sculpture Gardens in Purchase, NY
producer: Anthony Sheldonhmor
narrator: Efrem Zimbalist, Jr.
"Reading rainbow"
host: Levar Burton
"3-2-1 contact"
More educational programming